Guide to the Robert D. Miller papers, [ca. 1933-1998]
Miller, Robert D. papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Robert D. Miller papers, [ca. 1933-1998]
21-13-3960
(Robert Demorest), Miller 1919-
6.3 cubic feet.
Correspondence, course materials, research.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection includes personal and professional materials regarding his travels and work at Cornell
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of Soil Science. Robert Demorest Miller grew up in Columbia, Mo., earned a B.S. from the University of Missouri in 1940, an M.S. from the University of Nebraska in 1941, and a Ph.D. from Cornell University in 1948. During 1944-1945, he served as an air traffic and air defense controller in the Pacific in the Army Air Corps. On August 28, 1945, he was a member of a small advance party sent to Atsugi Air Base near Tokyo to prepare for the major American landings beginning the occupation of Japan. Shortly after landing, he raised the first American flag over Japan, on the radio mast of a C-47, two days before American combat troops began the actual armed occupation. He wrote about his wartime experiences in the book: "Descent from Niitaka, 1941-1945: First Flag Over Japan." After the war, he worked at the University of California at Berkeley, returning to Cornell in 1952 where he remained until his retirement in 1987. From 1964 to 1965, he served as assistant to the Provost Dale Corson and from 1967 to 1971 as dean of the faculty, in which position he played a role in the peaceful resolution of the Cornell '69 crisis, remaining a lifelong friend of President James Perkins. He is considered by his colleagues to be a "Founding Father" of soil physics. Robert Miller died on April 11, 2011.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection includes personal and family materials including an "auto log" travel diary kept by Miller's mother Flora Grace Ernst Miller from the family's 1933-1934 trip to Germany; materials relating to Miller's World War II experiences and the preparation of his book about them titled Descent from Niitaka; a letter to the Committee on the Armed Services regarding his perspectives on gays in the military; correspondence as Dean of the Faculty and later (to 1975); Cornell '69 materials; scientific correspondence, 1975-2010; materials relating to trips to Russia, 1973 and 1982; letters from James Perkins; slides and photograph albums from scientific trips; and publications and conference papers. course preparation material; material, photos, and slides relating to trips to Takutsk, Moscow, and others; awards; also business correspondence; publications and reprints.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Miller, R. D.1919-; Miller, Flora Grace Ernst.; Perkins, James Alfred, 1911-1998.; Cornell University.Dean of Faculty.; New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences.Dept. of Crop and Soil Sciences.
Subjects:
Airmen--United States.; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Pacific Ocean.; Military meteorologists--United States.; Soil science.; Germany--Description and travel.; Germany--Politics and government--1933-1945.; Russia--Description and travel.; College students--Political activity.; Willard Straight takeover, 1969.
Places:
Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
See also the Robert D. Miller. Oral Histories, #13-6-1285 and Merritt Miller papers, #4583.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Cornell University Material and Correspondence
Boxes 1, 6
Material and Correspondence on Cornell '69
James Perkins
Series II. Correspondence (Academic, Scientific, and Personal)
Box 1, 2, 6
Series III. Reprints
Box 3
Series IV. Courses
Box 3
Agronomy Course 607 R.D. Miller-Overheads-Soil Physics Part 1 Statics
Agronomy Course 607 R.D. Miller-Overheads-Soil Physics Part 2 Dynamics
Agronomy Course 607 R.D. Miller, Course Materials
Series V. Manuscripts and Lectures
Box 3, 6
Series VI. Slides and Photos
Box 3, 6
Yakutsk, Ice, Students
Doctoral Students' Slides, Work, Scaling, RDM's Slides
Other Slides
Series VII. Trips
Box 3, 4, 6, 7
Series VIII. Awards
Box 5, 6
Series IX. Personal and Family Materials
Box 4-7
Series X. World War II Materials
Boxes 5, 6
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Cornell University Material and Correspondence
  - Material and Correspondence on Cornell '69
    - Events of 1969 at Cornell (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Contains disks, photos, journals, and notes
    - Cornell Post '69 Materials 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Cornell '69 Liberalism and the Crisis of the American University by Donald A. Downs, with comments by R.D. Miller
    - Cornell Post '69 Materials 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Newspaper Clippings about '69 and Letter Correspondence with Cornell Faculties
    - Cornell Post '69 Materials 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      The Chimes of Freedom Flashing by Caleb S. Rossiter. Removed and catalogued separately.
    - Cornell Post '69 Materials 4, 1971-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Transcript of Statement, Correspondence James Perkins (1995), and others
    - Cornell Post '69 Materials 5, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes "A Failure to Communicate: James Perkins, COSEP, and Black Power at Cornell" Honors Thesis by Eric Rauchway and An Article by Keith R. Johnson
    - Cornell Post '69 Materials 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Miscellany, contains calender (1967-1968),a thesis draft by unknown author, Cornell University Student Faculty Board on Student Conduct Notice of Hearing(1968), a photo, notes, and a letter from Davis (2003)
    - Cornell '69 Post-event, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Cornell '69 More Post-event Materials: Downs, Rossiter, others, 1989-1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Collection of Newspaper on the 20th Anniversary of the Willard Straight Hall Takeover and Speech Draft, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - WSH 1989, 1, WSH Aftermath, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - WSH 1989, 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - WSH 1989, 3, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Newspaper and Journal Collection
    - General Legislation of the University Faculty and Extracts from Its Records, 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Materials Relating to Cornell in 1969, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Includes a private letter to his brothers and sisters describing his perspective on the situation, correspondence, clippings, Newsweek magazine, speeches, Henderson Commission information
    - Oral history, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      Transcript of an oral history interview conducted by Gould P. Colman as part of the Challenge to Governance Project. With index and correspondence regarding the oral history and its restrictions. See also archives 13-6-1285 for the audio tapes.
    - Cornell 1969 legacy materials, 1990s (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Includes information and correspondence regarding the death of Perkins, Perkins prize, Ari Van Tienhoven Tom Jones, DVD-1764 of "Cornell 1969: Key Issues Then and Now. A University Faculty Forum, 3 May 1999, Kennedy Hall;" "The 30th Anniversary of WSH Takeover" panel discussion, Memorial Room, Willard Straight Hall, 19 April 1999, the DVD also includes relevant news clippings. Also a copy of a 1978 letter sent to Perkins from the President of Oberlin College Robert Fuller about increasing enrollment of black students that Perkins forwarded to Miller in 1995.
  - James Perkins
    - Copy of Correspondence of James A. Perkins and Robert D. Miller, 1970-1998 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence with James A. Perkins, 1970-2003 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence between James A. Perkins and John R. Silber (President of Boston University), and Newspaper Clippings about Them, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Invitations, Photos, and Pamphlets for James A. Perkins Prize for Interracial Understanding and Harmony, 1992-2006 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series II. Correspondence (Academic, Scientific, and Personal)
  - Correspondence with Cornell University and Some Other Institutions, 1956-1966 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Scientific Correspondence with Dean of Faculty, 1967-Spring 1971 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, Fall 1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, Spring 1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, Spring 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, Fall 1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, Spring 1974 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, Fall 1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, Spring 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Fall 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Spring 1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Fall 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Spring 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Fall 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Spring 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Contains Correspondence with Frank H.T. Rhodes and Alfred E. Kahn
  - Correspondence, Fall 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Contains Correspondence with Alfred E. Kahn
  - Correspondence, Spring 1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Fall 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Spring 1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Fall 1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Dean of the Faculty Correspondence (Not Related to Cornell '69) 1, 1965-1977 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Contains a sub-series of National Science Foundation
  - Dean of the Faculty Correspondence (Not Related to Cornell '69) 2, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Scientific Correspondence, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Scientific Correspondence, 1988-2009 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - John A. Crowl, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Thomas W. Jones, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Frank H. T. Rhodes, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Personal Correspondence and Photos (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Business Correspondence, 1940-1952 (Box 2)
  - Morris Bishop Correspondence, 1962, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Includes correspondence from daughter Anne Miller, Herbert Cahoon of the Pierpont Morgan library and Morris Bishop regarding Anne's interest in witchcraft and desire to become a witch. Also correspondence regarding an amusing anecdote at Alice Cook's retirement involving David Burak and a joke about the Cornell mace.
  - 50th Anniversary Correspondence, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Correspondence regarding Robert and Beulah's anniversary. Correspondence include Keith Kennedy, Dale Corson, and war buddy Captain Walter Huckbee.
  - Dean of Faculty, 1967, 1969, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Correspondence and clipping regarding his election to the position of Dean of Faculty from Royse Murphy and Rolph Fairchild. Also a thank you note to a Mrs. Burton (a figure from his childhood) from Miller describing his work. Also a note of congratulations on retirement from Marlin Cline.
  - Presidential Correspondence, Various (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Includes letters and photographs from Perkins, Corson, Rhodes. Also a program from the Cornell Centennial Dinner. A photograph of Perkins shaking hands with Tom Jones inscribed "Without Bob Miller's cool head there would be no handshake."
  - Family Correspondence, Various (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Letters from Miller's father Dean Merritt Miller and one to his wife.
  - Correspondence to wife Beulah "Buty" from Russia, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Letters and ephemera sent to his wife while he was in Russia
  - Scientific Correspondence, Various (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Letters from colleagues and grad students. Includes letter to Dale Corson on soil physics. Also a floppy disk (FD-340) of soil correspondence
  - Edward Ershov Correspondence, 1970s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 14)
    Correspondence Miller's trip to Moscow State University and Ershov's visit to Cornell. Includes photographs of Ershov and of Russian trip.
  - Edward Miller Correspondence, Various (Box 6, Folder 16)
    Scientific correspondence with Miller's brother Professor Edward E Miller of the University of Wisconsin.
- Series III. Reprints
  - Robert D. Miller, Articles on > 0°, 1949-1971 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Robert D. Miller, Articles and Papers on < 0°, 1, 1971- (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Robert D. Miller, Articles and Papers on < 0°, 2, 1971- (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes some slides
  - Robert D. Miller, Articles and Papers on < 0°, 3, 1971- (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Robert D. Miller, Repints: Extra Copies (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Review Copy of Capillary Thermodynamics in Serially Porous Media, with Implications for Randomly Porous Media, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series IV. Courses
  - Agronomy Course 607 R.D. Miller-Overheads-Soil Physics Part 1 Statics
    - Soil Particles, Mechanical Analysis, Representative Samples, Textual Triangle, Closely Packed Spheres (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Soil Composition, Definitions, Idiosyncrasies (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Water Contend, Bulk Density, Neutron Probe (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Forces, Ideal Gas Law, Properties of Water, Static Equilibrium in Force Field (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Surface Tension, Capillary Rice, Bubbles, Phase Barriers (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Wetting and Drying, Hysteresis, Air Entry, Independent Domains (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Haines and Fisher Analyses, Terzaghi Equation, Aitchison's Concept, Synder's Work (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Clay Minerals, Electrophoresis and Electroosmosis, Helmholz-Schmolvchowski Equation, Ideal Diffuse Electrical Double Layer, Dispersion (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Agronomy Course 607 R.D. Miller-Overheads-Soil Physics Part 2 Dynamics
    - Recapitulation, Component Potentials, Adsorption Versus Capillary Space (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Flow in Saturated Soils, Darcy's Law, Kozeny Equations, Geometric Mean Diameter (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Miscible Displacement, Dispersion and Diffusion (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Method of Images, Electrostatic Analogue, Flow Nets, Dupuit Equation (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Flow in Unsaturated Soils, Equation of Continuity, Diffusivity, Available Water Range (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Scale Modelling, Grain, Substance and Forle Analogues, Scaling Statics, Scaling Dynamics (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Coupling of Transport Processes, Frost Heave, Freezing and Thawing Versus Wetting and Drying, Schofield's Work (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Agronomy Course 607 R.D. Miller, Course Materials
    - Course Materials 1 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Course Materials 2 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Series V. Manuscripts and Lectures
  - Papers at '93 SSA Meeting, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Capillary Conductivity of A Plate Perforated with Cylindrical Holes, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Draft of A Revision to Hillel, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Prepared as an addendum to a revised version of Hillel's Soil and Water, Physical Principles and Processes
  - Calculations on Various Topics, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Scientific work and lectures from Russia trip, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Manuscript and reprint (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Illustrations and drawings for papers (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Consulting, 1980s (Box 6, Folder 20)
    Reports on thruway, pipeline and cold region soil heaving projects
  - Calculation notebooks (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Skits and Speeches (Box 6, Folder 23)
    Skits and speeches written, namely for retirements of staff in the Agronomy Department. Includes items regarding Mark Barlow, Marlin Cline, Mike Peech, Ed Lemon, Bob Musgrave, Earl Stone, Paul Zwerman, Wright, Brady, Aldrich, others. Also audio tapes (tr-10890 Zwerman, Drosdoff; tr-10891 Lemon; tr-10892 Inceptisol, Peech, Zwerman, Drosdoff) and slides of these speeches.
- Series VI. Slides and Photos
  - Yakutsk, Ice Sandw, Students
    - Secondary Heaving HRB, Loch, Torrance, Cass, Hoekstra, Koopmans (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Swelling Soil, Colbeck, Calgary 79, Dirksen (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Doctoral Students' Slides, Work, Scaling, RDM's Slides
    - Field Photos, Caldwell F, Taber, Beskow, Miller Baker Kiolian, Römkens (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Phase Barrier, Massive Ice, O'NGM; Sunder, Scaling (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - P.Black, Horiguichi, Perfect, Massive Ice, Seminar 1981 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Other Slides
    - Slides of RMD Experimental Apparatus (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Chahal, Gypsum (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Experiment photographs and presentation diagrams (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Series VII. Trips
  - Permafrost III. Edmanton, Canada, Pictures of Experimental Apparatus, Pictures of Freezing-related Phenomena, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Slides
  - Pipeline Consulting Trips, 1980-1983 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence with Northwest Alaskan Pipeline, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Slides from Yakutsk Siberia Trip, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Negatives of Many Presentation Slides and Yakutsk Trip Pictures, 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Negatives of Many Presentation Slides and Yakutsk Trip Pictures, 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photos of Trip to Siberia and Permafrost Conference, Album 1, July, 1973 (Box 4)
    Also contains pictures of Moscow
  - Photos of Trip to Siberia and Permafrost Conference, Album 2, July, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Materials Related to Trip to Siberia and Permafrost Conference, 1, July, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Photos, Correspondence, Meeting Notes
  - Materials Related to Trip to Siberia and Permafrost Conference, 2, July, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Correspondence, Memorandum, Schedule, and Guidebooks
  - Moscow, 1, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Correspondence, Travel Materials
  - Moscow, 2, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Correspondence, Slides
  - Photos of Trip to Moscow, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Moscow Lectures Materials, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Film of Trip, F-365 (Box 5)
  - Slides (Box 5)
  - Unidentified Travel Photos (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Forms from the U.S.S.R. Embassy regarding trip to Russia, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Photo Album of Travels, 1930s (Box 7)
    Includes photographs from trips to Europe, including Germany, Munich, Heidelberg, Oberwesel, Burg Schonburg, Dresden, Nordlingen, Frankfurt, Dinklesbuhl, Austria, Innsbruch, France, Verdun, England, Stonehenge, Scotland, Edinburgh, golfing, Ireland, Lyons Kansas salt mine, geoogy field trip, Boulder Colorado, Bill Cargill, Dr. Bronson, Wyoming, William C. Warnerson, possibly University of Missouri, family photos, tap day,
  - Photo Album of Negatives from European trip, 1934 (Box 7)
- Series VIII. Awards
  - Certificate of Appreciation - The Federal Inspector, June 28, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Faculty-Alumni Award - Alumni Association of the University of Missouri-Columbia, September 21, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Faculty-Alumni Award - University of Missouri-Columbia (Box 5)
  - Recognition of Outstanding Achievement in Agronomy - American Society of Agronomy Northeastern Branch, June 28, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Certificats from American Society of Agronomy, Soil Science Society of America (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Series IX. Personal and Family Materials
  The papers of Prof. Miller's father Merritt Finley Miller are in the University of Missouri archives and the Missouri State Historical Society archives
  - High School Columbia (Box 4, Folder 12)
    This is Prof. Miller's high school. The folder includes his correspondence with the school, speech to 1961 class, and a German song book.
  - Prof. Miller's writings (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Humorous (re: neighbor's dog), letter re '82 trip to Moscow, notes and account of '73 trip to Siberia, Retirement of Nile Brady-Sketch
  - Family Photo (Box 5)
  - Obituaries, 2011 (Box 5)
  - Article on Robert D. Miller and Edward E. Miller: "The Agronomy Brothers", 1960 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Family History, Newspaper copy of a report on Edward Mix, First Cousin of Merritt F. Miller, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - East-Central Illinois Landforms and Ecosystems in the Making 20,000 Years by Elisabeth M. Hanson, 2011 (Box 4)
    Elisabeth Hanson is Prof. Miller's sister.
  - Europe Autolog, 1 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Records family's 1933-34 sabbatical trip to Germany throughout Europe, kept by Prof. Miller's mother Flora Grace Ernst Miller. Front page picture drawn by youthful Prof. Miller
  - Europe Autolog, 2 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Records family's 1933-34 sabbatical trip to Germany throughout Europe.
  - Europe Autolog, 3 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Letter from Sam Walton, the founder of Walmart, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - A Photograph of Obama, with the Signature of Joe Biden Printed (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Statement of Elisabeth Hanson (Prof. Muller's sister) regarding Being on the Andrea Doria, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Autobiography of Carl Julius Ernest (Prof. Miller's Maternal Grandfather) (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Carl Julius Ernst's Papers are in the Nebraska Historical Society
  - Correspondence with Paul R. Day, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Copy of Note Scrap and Remark Book of Edward Eddy Miller (Prof. Miller's Grandfather), with Prof. Miller's Introduction (Box 4, Folder 24)
    E.E.Miler served in Ohio regiment. The original is in Ohio Historical Society collection.
  - Prof. Miller's Address and Appointment Books 1-3, 1978-1985 (Box 5)
  - Prof. Miller's Name Card (Box 5)
  - A Small Electrical Piece of Lab Equipment with A Brass Part Machined by Prof. Miller (Box 5)
  - Photographs, Various (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Includes photos as a baby, wedding photo, family photos, photos from Cornell, image of Miller being interviewed by Bob Simon during Cornell 69.
  - Personal files, Various (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Includes 1966 family letter, files regarding employment, passports, letter to the editor about Jack Musick, pamphlet "The Story of an Emigrant Boy", awards, invite to a cocktail party from Adlai Stevenson, University of Missouri 1940 diploma, account book kept by Miller 1935-1936, Grandparent book describing the life or Miller's sister Elisabeth Marie Miller describing her life which is informative about Robert's early life as well, birth certificate, resumes, Ithaca Journal article about potholes, envelope containing keys that may have belonged to his office in Caldwell Hall.
  - The University in Transition by James A. Perkins, 1966 (Box 6)
    Inscribed to Miller by Perkins.
  - The Crescent Yearbook, 1935 (Box 6)
    David h. Hickman High School yearbook, annotated by Miller and classmates.
  - Prof. Miller's Address and Appointment Books, 1962-1966 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook from Junior and High School, and College, 1931-1939 (Box 7)
    Items from Jefferson Junior High School Columbia Missouri, Hickman High School, programs, report cards, photographs, Boy Scouts of America cards, University of Missouri items, Barnwarmin' programs, Alpha Zeta material, correspondence.
- Series X. World War II Materials
  - Materials Prepared for the Book Descent from Niitaka (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Appendix, First Draft (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Appendix, Set-Asides (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Memorandum and Agreement of Descant from Niitaka, Responses Received after the Publication (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence in Search of Information and Responses (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Material Prepared for History Classes at Ithaca High School (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence with D-Day Museum, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Framed Photo (Box 5)
    Explosion of American B 24 bomber, taken by Prof. Miller beside foxhole
  - Slides (Box 5)
  - Slides and Negatives from Pacific (Box 5)
  - World War II and Military Materials (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Includes orders, correspondence about his memorabilia with museums, photographs, sketches, correspondence with the Veterans Administration and regarding his lectures to high schools. Also a letter written to the Committee on the Armed Services from April 3, 1993 on Miller's thoughts on gays in the military.
  - CDs of photographs related to WWII, 1423-1425 (Box 5)
    Niitaka photos (raising flag, Nagasaki), Interview Circus, Museum Presentation (D-Day)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Books Removed From Collection, Cataloged Separately:
Perkins, A. James. The University in A Restless Decade. New York, NY: The International Council for Educational Development, 1972.
Miller, D. Robert. Descent from Niitaka 1941-1945 First Flag over Japan. Ithaca, NY: Cayuga Press, 2002